Guide to the James R. Sims papers, 1924-2002 MS 596
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
James R. Sims papers, 1924-2002
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Sims, Jim
MS 596
1 Linear Feet (1 carton)
The papers contain documents, photographs and printed material which document the career of James R. Sims, who taught civil engineering at Rice Institute (later Rice University) beginning in 1942 as an instructor, to becoming the Herman and George R. Brown Chair of Civil Engineering until his retirement in 1987. He then served as the Herman and George R. Brown Professor Emeritus of Civil Engineering from 1987 until his death in 2009.
Biographical Sketch
James R. Sims helped change the face of Rice in the '60s and '70s by leading a $35 million campus renovation project while simultaneously chairing the then-Civil Engineering Department. A 1941 graduate of Rice Institute with a degree in civil engineering, Sims worked briefly as a structural engineer before returning to the university as an instructor in 1942. He earned a master's degree and doctorate in engineering at the University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign in 1950 and 1956, respectively. The pinnacle in Sims' career was serving as the national American Society of Civil Engineers (ASCE) president, a post he held in 1982 in which he advocated the interests of more than 72,000 civil engineers across the nation. Sims also fought tirelessly for stringent educational standards and ethical behavior in the profession and led various committees and working groups at the national, state and local levels of ASCE. The Texas Society of Professional Engineers named Sims Engineer of the Year in 1976 and the Engineers' Council of Houston gave him its Award of Honor in 1977. He was named Rice Engineering Alumni Outstanding Engineering Alumnus in 1983. The James Redding Sims Scholarship in Civil Engineering, administered by the Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, is an endowed scholarship at Rice. James Redding Sims was the Herman and George R. Brown Professor Emeritus of Civil and Environmental Engineering and former vice president of business affairs, when he died in 2009 at the age of 91.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain documents, photographs and printed material which document the career of James R. Sims, who taught civil engineering at Rice Institute (later Rice University) beginning in 1942 as an instructor, to becoming the Herman and George R. Brown Chair of Civil Engineering until his retirement in 1987. He then served as the Herman and George R. Brown Professor Emeritus of Civil Engineering from 1987 until his death in 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Access restrictions
This material is open for research.
Arrangement
The James R. Sims papers are organized into two series:
Series I: Rice University
Series II: Personal
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges
Document Types
photographs
Subjects (Persons)
Brown, George R., 1898-1983 -- Correspondence; Ryon, Lewis B.
- Series I: Rice University, 149118
  - Rice University Engineering, 149119
    - Engineering Department charimen, 1957-1987, 149120 (Folder 1)
    - Engineering experiments, photographs, 149121 (Folder 2)
    - Early Engineering graduate transcript examples, 149122 (Folder 3)
    - Engineering Department, photographs, 149123 (Folder 4)
    - Civil Engineering Department, photographs, 149124 (Folder 5)
    - Civil Engineering Department, history, 1957, 1995-1996, 149125 (Folder 6)
    - Civil Engineering Department, curriculum, 1961-1963, 149126 (Folder 7)
    - Civil Engineering Department, meeting, August 16, 1993, 149127 (Folder 8)
    - Civil Engineering Department, reorganization, April 2001, 149128 (Folder 9)
    - Mecahnical Engineering Laboratory isntructions, 149129 (Folder 10)
    - Mechanical Engineering 300 report, 1939, 149130 (Folder 11)
    - Mechanical Lab, background, 149131 (Folder 12)
    - A.J. Hartsook Chair, history, 149132 (Folder 13)
    - Lewis B. Ryon Chair in Engineering, 1972, 1986-1987, 149133 (Folder 14)
    - George R. Brown Chair, correspondence, information, 1963-1996, 149134 (Folder 15)
    - "Some Reflections on Engineering at Rice Institute", parts 1 & 2, 149135 (Folder 16)
  - Correspondence (Includes photographs), 149136 (Folder 17)
  - Rice campus scenes, photographs, 149137 (Folder 18)
  - Excerpts from "Odyssey of a Freshman, 1912" by Harry M. Bulbrook, 1916, 149138 (Folder 19)
  - "Facts Published About Rice that are not True", 149139 (Folder 20)
  - References to the Polytechnic School, chronology of events from the Board of Trustees' minutes, 149140 (Folder 21)
  - Lewis B. Ryon, 149141
    - Ryon Symposium, 1996, 149142 (Folder 22)
    - Ryon Laboratory photographs, 149143 (Folder 23)
    - Album "Presented to L.B. Ryon at Testimonial Dinner Commemorating 40 years at Rice Institute," 1957, 149144 (Folder 24)
    - Photographs and loose materials from album, 1957, 149369 (Folder 25)
    - Ryon Building name, 149145 (Folder 26)
    - Ryon Laboratory groundbreaking, 1962 (Includes photographs), 149146 (Folder 27)
    - Ryon Laboratory dedication, November 12, 1965 (Includes photographs), 149147 (Folder 28)
    - Lewis B. & Mae R. Ryon biographical information, 1924, 1962-1996 (Includes photographs), 149148 (Folder 29)
    - Lewis B. and Mae R. Ryon gifts, 1959-1962, 1980-1986 (Includes photographs), 149149 (Folder 30)
  - Rice organizations, associations and awards, 149150
    - Civil/Environmental Engineering awards, April 18, 2002, 149151 (Folder 31)
    - Engineering Society and Engineering Matters notes from Rice Thresher, 149152 (Folder 32)
    - Engineering shows, details (Rice Engineering Society), 149153 (Folder 33)
    - Chi Epsilon chapter, Rice University, 1995, 149154 (Folder 34)
    - Association of Rice Alumni Gold Medal, 1997-1999, 149155 (Folder 35)
    - Alumni Awards lists, 149156 (Folder 36)
    - Engineers' Council for Professional Development, 1955-1961, 149157 (Folder 37)
    - Rice Engineering Alumni (REA) article, 1986, 149158 (Folder 38)
    - Rice ACSE student chapter, 1942, 1995-1996 (Includes photographs), 149159 (Folder 39)
- Series II: Personal, 149160
  - Louis D. Spaw Anniversary, June 19, 1999 (photograph), 149161 (Folder 40)
  - Report of the City Planning Commission, Houston, Texas, 1929, 149162 (Folder 41)
  - Citicorp Center information, 1995-1996, 149163 (Folder 42)
  - Franz Brotzen, 1995, 149164 (Folder 43)
  - Project Mohole (consultant), 1964-1967, 149165 (Folder 44)